<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Recompute Podcast | </title>
    <link>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Recompute Podcast</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://recompute-pk.github.io/images/logo_hu127f1887e0d4c9f26f7a9283e7f80760_127742_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Recompute Podcast</title>
      <link>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>ReCompute with Sabieh Anwar | Romance of Knowledge | Staying rooted | What LUMS gets right | Podcast # 3</title>
      <link>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/podcast03-sabieh-anwar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/podcast03-sabieh-anwar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dr. Sabieh Anwar hardly needs any introduction in Pakistani academia, but Recompute.pk has taken a   different perspective in this podcast. We went through a reflective cross section of his life, first when he was a student, then his phase as a young scholar or a faculty member joining a university in Pakistan, and finally his experience as a dean of an important STEM school at LUMS. We sincerely think that any faculty member who wants to do anything creative and meaningful in his or her teaching, no doubt, must bring that element in the classroom in front of the students, but has also to creatively deal with departmental constraints and the wider university culture and policy matters simultaneously. By moving through Sabieh Anwar’s reflective journey, we feel that students, faculty members and academic administrators will all have considerable food for their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/guVlo2SOWcw&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;the-person-that-you-are-was-it-your-university-or-school-education-that-helped-you-shape-that-way-or-was-it-the-way-you-were-brought-up-by-your-parents&#34;&gt;The person that you are, was it your university or school education that helped you shape that way or was it the way you were brought up by your parents?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve given me a chance to reflect upon such vast topics, it’s a difficult task. My father is no more, but after his departure I feel more strongly about his deep impact on my life. I was in grade 3 when we came back to Lahore from England after my father’s PhD there. At first I was admitted to a famous English-medium school, it is still there and perhaps thousands of students are still studying there. But I remember that there was a ban on speaking in Urdu there, with a fine if one was caught speaking in it. But soon my father realized that I should be sent to a school where they inculcate a national spirit. I still remember these words of “milli jazba” from him even though we did not understand it back then. So he put me in Crescent Model School, where there were big grounds, morning assembly with Quranic recitation and national anthem, declamation contests in both Urdu and English, student societies and sports. The best teachers from my father’s alma mater, Central Model School, had joined Crescent after retirement, and I believe it was the best decision made by my father, as these teachers really shaped our hearts, minds and morals. And they did this all, silently, without preaching. We were taught English really well there, but equally well was the way we read Urdu, while our teachers even used references from Arabic and Farsi. There was no inferiority complex of any sort there, there was a strange self-confidence – the kind that does not border on obnoxious pride or elitism. In short, it was a beautiful schooling experience. Secondly, at home, our elders were those who just loved Pakistan, some had even participated in the Pakistan Movement, and that had a deep imprint on my being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also due to my father, I had a craze about Physics, to the extent that I opted to do both Matric as well as O-levels, since the traditional matriculations didn’t go into deeper conceptual spaces. Almost every year our school used to take the top Board positions, but that year even though I topped within the school, I was fourth in the Board. Everyone advised us to take the Board to the court, but once more my father made such an important intervention and made me look ahead and to move on. For my FSc I went to Government College but apart from my studies I took part in parliamentary style of debating, to the extent that I was chosen for representing Pakistan’s debating team and we even went to New Zealand to compete internationally. Again, it was my father who pushed me towards this, since my school days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that when I wanted to do BSc in Physics, my father pushed me to do Electrical Engineering from UET instead, since there wasn’t any good university for basic Physics, and what a wonderful decision that was. During UET days we founded Khwarizmi Science Society which aimed to bring science to the public understanding to bridge the gap between students and science experts, and even to this day this society is alive and doing a wonderful job. My father never discouraged me from these activities, but he did bring a newspaper ad for Rhodes scholarship home one day, which I eventually received and went to Oxford after my undergrad. There I studied Physics to my heart’s content. We were at the cusp of Quantum computing in 2001 there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;compared-to-pakistani-universities-what-was-the-experience-of-oxford-like-as-a-student&#34;&gt;Compared to Pakistani universities, what was the experience of Oxford like, as a student?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It seemed like heaven to me! There was so much to do all over the university. I spent so much time in libraries there. There’s a real treasure of knowledge in each of the big libraries in England, not just at Oxford. A nostalgic feeling takes over when I see our ancestral books also preserved in their libraries. I do believe that if for some reasonUK gets destroyed today, it can all be built back to its glory from just one of those libraries. Secondly, we were spoiled for choice when it came to seminars, almost every day, so much was happening outside the classes. Even our Pakistan Discussion Forum organized two events on Iqbal and Rumi.
After Oxford, I went to Berkeley for my Postdoc for 2 years, and that was a wonderful experience as well. I thank God for being so kind to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;but-why-were-you-studying-so-much-you-did-matric-and-o-levels-in-parallel-then-bsc-then-phd-and-then-even-postdoc-was-it-a-given-that-youre-going-to-become-an-academician&#34;&gt;But why were you studying so much? You did Matric and O levels in parallel, then BSc then Phd, and then even Postdoc. Was it a given that you’re going to become an academician?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I had a romance with knowledge, with books, with Physics!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’d have to expand on that as there’s certainly some confusions out there in the modern academia, as some good academicians are turning towards industry for higher salaries, and some are aiming for that while remaining within university, but you had some other ideals it seems, as you’ve used this term of “romance”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than the grip that the knowledge had on my being, I think I was in love with the act of teaching – imparting that knowledge to my students. I think my training in debating and oratory really helped me in my classes, as otherwise Physics could be a very dry subject. I love to teach, it’s a process of catharsis for me. Even if I’m tired after the drudgery  of work, by the time I’m done with my class, I feel absolutely fresh. So, I’m in romance with not just the content of Physics, but also the act of imparting that knowledge to students. Secondly, I love the connections across the fields, e.g. the connection between Biology and Physics. The romance also comes from the “bigger picture” of Science or Physics, that of Schrodinger and Heisenberg, which Freeman Dyson terms as a bird’s eye view or “Shaheen’s” view. I love how Physics is so fundamental and it lets one think and know about one’s being, one’s history. All of it with such small vocabulary yet with such a world of meaning and expression. Would this not build nostalgia and romance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;since-weve-already-transitioned-into-teaching-can-you-elaborate-upon-the-choices-you-had-to-make-after-being-done-with-postdoc-for-instance-you-could-have-stayed-in-the-west-or-could-have-joined-a-public-university-like-your-father-but-you-chose-a-young-small-private-university-like-lums&#34;&gt;Since we’ve already transitioned into teaching, can you elaborate upon the choices you had to make after being done with Postdoc? For instance, you could have stayed in the West or could have joined a public university like your father but you chose a young small private university like LUMS.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The decision of returning back to your roots is made before going outside, not when you’re there, so that was always the case with me. By God I tried getting into UET, but due to their policies I couldn’t fit anywhere as I had partly done Electrical Engineering and partly Physics. Also, during my interview at UET the VC asked me a non-technical question, and when I started answering in Urdu, he firmly interrupted, “Gentleman, in English please!”. Around 2006-7 when LUMS hadn’t yet started School of Science and Engineering (SSE) its project director visited Berkeley during my Postdoc, and invited me to apply to SSE. I gave a faculty talk at LUMS. Later, Dr. Asad Abidi of UCLA became SSE’s first dean, he invited me there and interviewed me and then gave me an offer for LUMS. LUMS turned out to be a great choice, its biggest factor has been freedom and a lack of strict hierarchy. I’m not the most senior professor at SSE and yet I’ve been elected as a Dean, so in this respect it is like the best universities of the West.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;speaking-of-the-best-universities-theres-a-race-for-international-rankings-within-pakistani-universities-and-those-who-are-faring-far-better-than-lums-as-far-as-the-checklists-and-ranking-formulae-are-not-the-first-choice-of-students-and-parents-like-the-way-lums-is-what-is-lums-doing-right-that-other-universities-of-pakistan-are-missing&#34;&gt;Speaking of the best universities, there’s a race for international rankings within Pakistani universities, and those who are faring far better than LUMS as far as the checklists and ranking formulae, are not the first choice of students and parents, like the way LUMS is. What is LUMS doing right that other universities of Pakistan are missing?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will speak on behalf of my own school of SSE. Our strength is our hiring. In Pakistan, our universities don’t have the right hiring mechanism worked out. On the one hand even if the best Pakistani PhD from MIT or Stanford wants to apply to Pakistani universities, he or she wouldn’t be able to work out a valid email address to send the CV to. On the other hand, the selection panel will have all sorts of irrelevant people like the VC of a university, high court’s judge, public service commission’s member, secretary education representative, and an arbitrary subject specialist. Which means, the right kind of judgment is not being done at the time of hiring. LUMS, on the other hand, does all it’s hard work at the time of hiring. We have around 100 faculty members at SSE now, and they are more or less all like-minded. We are passionate about teaching as well as research, and hence there’s equality amongst us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking is a qualitative affair, not a quantitative one completely, just like the relationship between a teacher and a student isn’t quantitative, just like learning isn’t a quantitative entity. And LUMS is qualitatively different from others. But I’ve seen this qualitative element at Namal, and at nascent stages of GIKI, at Habib, at QAU at one time. Faculty hiring and promotions, VC selection, these should all have qualitative elements, not just arbitrary assignment of quantitative marks per criteria. Like Nur-ud-din Zengi didn’t find Salahuddin Ayyubi through a quantitative process, you need that trusting qualitative ‘nazar’ to find what you’re looking for, at least at leadership level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lums-has-carved-out-its-own-selection-process-which-is-different-from-the-one-proposed-by-hec-policies-it-seems-and-it-is-surely-working-for-you-what-lets-lums-disagree-with-the-principles-set-forth-by-various-accreditation-bodies&#34;&gt;LUMS has carved out its own selection process which is different from the one proposed by HEC policies, it seems. And it is surely working for you. What lets LUMS disagree with the principles set forth by various accreditation bodies?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though we are a private university, we are not let off the hook completely by HEC or PEC. These accreditors have almost become a meta-university and all others a sub-campus of it. But whenever they become a hurdle in creativity, what is required by academic leadership is to rightly engage with the leadership of accreditation bodies, to present arguments to them with reason and respect. People at HEC and PEC have also studied in good universities, many from outside of Pakistan, but nobody tries really to engage with them, nobody even talks to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I strongly believe that it is the old ideas that are holding back our universities. The whole world has moved on and insha’Allah we will find creative openings in our landscape too. At SSE we have almost a common first year across schools and students can make up their minds along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;youre-very-hopeful-about-the-future-even-regarding-our-public-universities-and-accreditation-bodies-but-unlike-lums-sse-which-has-a-very-qualitatively-different-approach-to-faculty-hiring-of-like-minded-individuals-as-a-consequence-of-which-academic-freedom-makes-total-sense-however-there-are-many-other-private-universities-that-have-already-quantitatively-hired-a-mixed-bag-of-faculty-members-based-on-arbitrary-paper-publications-etc-do-you-think-think-those-departments-and-universities-have-hope-are-there-any-ingredients-that-if-placed-correctly-at-such-a-later-stage-can-still-set-them-off-in-the-right-direction&#34;&gt;You’re very hopeful about the future, even regarding our public universities and accreditation bodies, but unlike LUMS SSE which has a very qualitatively different approach to faculty hiring of like-minded individuals as a consequence of which academic freedom makes total sense, however, there are many other private universities that have already quantitatively hired a mixed bag of faculty members based on arbitrary paper publications etc, do you think think those departments and universities have hope? Are there any ingredients that if placed correctly at such a later stage can still set them off in the right direction?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe small experiments like Namal or Austrian University at Haripur need to succeed. The VC or Rector needs to be a satiated person who has no ambitions for himself, and instead is kind, giving and capable as a leader. Then the core faculty hiring needs to be done very meticulously, as that is going to be the catalyst. Intentions are especially important in the beginning. There’s a need for ‘jawaano ko peeron ka ustaad kar’ so new people with new thoughts and new spirits need to be cherished without any political interference. At LUMS another great aspect is that there’s zero political intervention when it comes to student induction or faculty hiring and promotion etc. Even the President of Pakistan or PM or corps commander cannot do anything. These ingredients along with merit, transparency allow a place like LUMS to not be influenced by anybody else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are many universities in Pakistan much bigger than LUMS, where there’s wonderful faculty working, all they need is an exemplary leadership that is more interested in their faculty’s career development than their own. This kind of leadership cannot be produced through an MBA program. It can be produced through reading Iqbal, through reading Quran, through reading history, it can be inspired through a hero portrayed in a novel, it can be catalyzed by an event. The kind of leadership that can create Pakistan, that can construct our nuclear program, why can’t we have such leadership in universities? Within universities leaders need to be selected on merit, so they can become exemplary for everyone. We are naturally emotional and missionary, with exemplary leadership most of the faculty members will follow their leaders to wonderful spaces. The processes for head hunting VCs, deans and heads of departments need to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;you-had-already-found-a-pretty-sound-lums-when-you-joined-it-but-coming-to-your-phase-of-deanship-now-is-there-any-gap-that-you-at-the-leadership-of-sse-want-to-fill-still&#34;&gt;You had already found a pretty sound LUMS when you joined it, but coming to your phase of deanship now, is there any gap that you at the leadership of SSE want to fill still?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gap that I’m trying to bridge is our connection with Pakistan. Firstly, our message needs to reach out to others, but not as an elite looking down upon the rest, but just as a humble dissemination of whatever good idea we’re practicing. For this important mission, I’ve created a science communication cell, started off a website and videos. Language is important, I’ve asked all my MS and PhD theses to have an Urdu title as well as summary. I’ve also started communicating with policy makers in the same spirit. Secondly, I’m inspired by the need to integrate interdisciplinary areas such as brain or neuroscience and engineering. I want to create a center for clinical innovation that disrupts the silos of pre-medical and pre-engineering in Pakistan, where engineers and scientists can work and research in tandem with clinicians. If this barrier can’t be broken at LUMS or a private university, it’s very hard to imagine it happening anywhere else. I want to create deeper academic links of SSE with fringe areas such as archeology, astronomy, geology. We already have two computer scientists who have been hired in our Biology department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;there-needs-to-be-a-buy-in-from-all-your-faculty-members-so-that-this-wonderful-vision-of-their-dean-could-be-achieved-is-it-because-of-a-democratic-process-through-which-you-were-elected-as-a-dean-that-makes-this-possible&#34;&gt;There needs to be a buy-in from all your faculty members so that this wonderful vision of their dean could be achieved. Is it because of a democratic process through which you were elected as a dean that makes this possible?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if one comes through as a result of a democratic process, he could still act dictatorially. As a dean I have to continuously be in a democratic dialogue with all my faculty in order that this vision becomes a reality. I have made two principles for myself as a dean: 1) I have to positively keep on surprising my faculty, by making their life easier without their asking for it, by enabling their research ideals, instead of bureaucratizing it. 2) I want to prioritize ideas that have a long-term impact. I want to give space to relevant as well as unusual research directions that don’t find home anywhere else. Lastly, I wish to see our faculty as well as students learning about learning.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ReCompute with Bilal Zafar | Types and roles of universities, importance of purpose alignment, working with the industry | Podcast # 2</title>
      <link>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/podcast02-bilal-zafar/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/podcast02-bilal-zafar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-bilal&#34;&gt;Why Bilal?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilal Zafar is co-founder of 10XEngineers, a design services organization in the domain of computer engineering. Before that he was VP Engineering at Lampró Méllon, another design services company. But for most of his professional life he worked at QualComm in San Diego on custom and semi-custom implementation of chip designing. Anyone having a Samsung smartphone with a Snapdragon chip on it, is likely using technology that Bilal&amp;rsquo;s team had a hand in building. Before that, he did his PhD and postdoc at University of Southern California and BS at GIK Institute. In summary, he&amp;rsquo;s a competent and successful engineer, a product in part of Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s best university of his graduation era.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/7W7rn9DLeT0&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-exactly-is-the-purpose-of-a-university&#34;&gt;What exactly is the purpose of a university?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a badly phrased question, just as it&amp;rsquo;s a badly phrased question to be asked to identify what&amp;rsquo;s the universal purpose of an airline or a convenience store. There are many roles, it all depends on who&amp;rsquo;s opening the store, where it is being opened, what kind of customers are they targeting. Same is the case with universities: a university is a tool to do a certain number of things, and it&amp;rsquo;s up to the given university to identify which of the purposes it specifically wants to serve. For instance, LUMS with its 5000 students would have a very different set of aims and the services it provides in the society, when compared to Allama Iqbal Open university, with about 3 lac enrolled students. So, there&amp;rsquo;s absolutely no comparison as these are two clearly different organizations, and it would be unfair to put them in any one bracket together. The only reason this question keeps popping up is because it is being asked by university professors who have a romantic notion of what a university ought to be, as opposed to a more utilitarian view.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-does-society-want-the-university-to-be&#34;&gt;What does society want the university to be?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want an unambiguous answer to the question you&amp;rsquo;d have to turn to the parents, the employers, the students, and they all would almost unanimously say that we want university to produce competent professionals who can get good jobs after university graduation, or that they should have a respectable stature in the society. So, if we look at the question from a pragmatic point of view, we&amp;rsquo;ll arrive at an answer on which the rest of the society will also be standing with us, otherwise if left to academicians who have way too many years inside a university, they will idealize and suggest that every university must be only like Harvard and Princeton. For instance, why isn&amp;rsquo;t India&amp;rsquo;s Indra Gandhi University not a role model, which produces more graduates every two years than all the Harvards and Princetons of the world combined. So, the contextual relevance needs to be clarified first. One of the largest university systems in the US is California community colleges, they don&amp;rsquo;t create knowledge per se, but their role is to produce the firemen, nurses, hairdressers, school teachers, and they are perfectly happy doing that service for the eighth largest GDP of the world. Hence, we must bracket this question so that we know which university is it that we&amp;rsquo;re talking about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For American public universities it is important to spend money on sports, because their students say that it is sports that gives them identity, a sense of being part of a community, and this is true outside the walls of the public university for an ordinary citizen on the street, hence it gets translated within university as well. For instance, in USC, the head sports coach used to earn many times more than the university’s president, which means they know how to align everything once their identity and purpose of existence is clear. Similarly, in Pakistan there should be all sorts of universities, there should be LUMS and Quaid-e-Azam universities with focus on creating new knowledge &amp;ndash; we can&amp;rsquo;t say that just because we are a poor nation we should only provide vocational trainings &amp;ndash; and there should be UETs too, and they should serve their respective and distinct purposes in society, as long as cumulatively they create a strong, diverse ecosystem in Pakistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;3-pakistani-universities-3-purposes-3-stories&#34;&gt;3 Pakistani universities, 3 purposes, 3 stories:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilal has had a chance, in Pakistani context, to think about this question of purpose of a university, for 3 different universities. One was GIKI, where he saw its best version as well as its downfall, and the question of purpose became an important question to trace the roots of the downfall. GIKI had absolute clarity of purpose &amp;ndash; to produce the best science and engineering professionals, and this purpose managed to seep into their people, processes and choices.
The second time Bilal was made to think about this question was at the design stages of Habib University. Habib wanted to build a strong liberal arts and humanities foundations but for a common man, and it was Bilal’s who convinced them that this is not going to happen as a common man doesn&amp;rsquo;t want their kids to become a teacher with a great MA in English, they want them to become doctors or engineers. So, if one wants a true liberal arts undergrad, one should target the elites, so that instead of going outside Pakistan, they could get the same quality at Habib. The whole point is that once this purpose is clear, it is a perfectly legitimate service to Pakistan. The other option was to keep the liberal arts foundations, but the core degrees should be very narrow and specialized like engineering or computing etc, so that the technical side of the students is also employable and competitive in the job market, and Habib went for that.
The third experience was at a private entity in Lahore, UCP, which mostly catered to the students belonging to small and medium scale business families, and hence about 25% of students at UCP opt for BBA, followed by CS. UCP is purely a profit making enterprise, hence the vision for UCP becomes very different, and its focus should be to make these students better businessmen as most of them are going to go back to their father&amp;rsquo;s or uncle&amp;rsquo;s shops or factories. In other words, UCP&amp;rsquo;s focus should be to improve its students’ business and ethical competencies that will help in their actual businesses. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if they&amp;rsquo;ve studied liberal arts. For Habib on the other hand, their students come from a financially sounder background, hence it makes sense that their vision is more focused on turning their students into risk-taking entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;alignment-as-first-principle&#34;&gt;Alignment as first principle:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is not too hard an exercise to do and does not require decades of leg work, especially for universities who have been around for decades. It just needs a clear-eyed view of what they&amp;rsquo;ve mainly been doing, and that&amp;rsquo;s their vision and their role in society. For example, it is impossible to imagine that Punjab University wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know at this stage the kind of role they&amp;rsquo;ve been playing in Pakistan. Secondly, there needs to be an alignment between the owner and the current vice chancellor. That&amp;rsquo;s about it, if these two ingredients are in place, the rest of the alignment can follow even overnight. Unlike Harvards and Princetons of the world, most of Pakistani universities don&amp;rsquo;t have lengthy red tapes or tedious processes to take care of. Here even the HEC&amp;rsquo;s chairman can be changed overnight, so the whole process of alignment shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take 25 years for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-hasnt-pakistan-produced-world-class-universities&#34;&gt;Why hasn’t Pakistan produced world class universities?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biggest problem is not regarding curriculum or textbooks. According to Bilal, Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s biggest problem is an acute dearth of professional competent individuals. To run a big, complicated country you need lots of competent professionals in all domains. Same is the case with the individuals and teams in universities or accreditor bodies responsible for curriculum design - they just are not competent enough to do their jobs. So, they end up replicating what they had studied perhaps 30 years ago, meanwhile the international industry keeps moving ahead. Amidst this famine of competency, Pakistan can have one or at most 4 LUMS-type institutions, not 178, and that&amp;rsquo;s the worrying structural problem! Though we can&amp;rsquo;t have 178 LUMS, surely we could have had 4 with the kind of output LUMS is producing. But don’t even have that because good, competent faculty members are disbursed and distributed in various universities. In addition to the structural problem, the institutional problem stems from the fact that perhaps there&amp;rsquo;s only one Syed Babar Ali in Lahore, one Habib group in Karachi. If we have more such people who are concerned about education, perhaps they can collect the distributed talent again. One recent example is how Umar Saif tried at ITU by gathering quality people and resources, to produce quality output. But this would solve the problem for a total of 4 Pakistani universities at best, the rest of them would remain the same, all aiming at ranking formulae instead of quality output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-dont-good-foreign-qualified-pakistanis-come-back&#34;&gt;Why don’t good foreign qualified Pakistanis come back?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there&amp;rsquo;s one more practical issue, in the form of limits to the spirit of nationalism. A standard university in Pakistan would offer a starting salary of about $1000 to a fresh PhD, that&amp;rsquo;s $12,000 per year. Someone like Bilal may be offered $15,000 per month outside Pakistan. This translates into absolutely different qualities of life, including kids’ education, health, security etc. But given this sharp diagnosis, does Bilal have any advice for those who have decided to stay in Pakistan, positively building forward?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice for a faculty member:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ideal of having a purpose and its alignment even applies to an individual. Any faculty member sitting in any university has to bring together his purpose, the resources available and his best strengths. For instance, someone can be very good at teaching. If that is the case, then that faculty member has to be at peace with not having much &amp;ldquo;impact factor&amp;rdquo; or having delayed promotions, and if he persists through this, he&amp;rsquo;ll feel fulfilled eventually. Same is the case with those who feel they are good at research. Some faculty members should reach out to a couple of good software houses and ask the professionals there to teach him as to what they want from university students, learn from their meetings, from their processes, and he should go back to university and teach the CS students what he&amp;rsquo;s learnt. In return he can at least solve the 20% of employment problem, as those software houses are bound to employ his students. So, playing to one&amp;rsquo;s strengths and callings should always work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice for a departmental head:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilal’s team is trying an experiment as a solution, one that bridges the gap between what the university produces and what the industry needs. It requires 3-4 months of remedial work, in the form of re-teaching fresh graduates courses that are fundamental to microprocessor chips designing. Because the related industry didn&amp;rsquo;t really exist in Pakistan previously, courses like digital logic design, computer architecture, data structures, embedded programming and systems weren&amp;rsquo;t streamlined in engineering universities and consequently most of EE or even computer engineering students didn&amp;rsquo;t take these courses seriously as they all wanted to major in Power or Telecom sector. This teaching of fundamentals can easily be done in a better and focused way in academia instead of them having to do this as remedial work. This is precisely the job of a head of department, to figure out the strengths of his department&amp;rsquo;s faculty, map it to a few industries, put his best resources and faculty together and purposefully streamline their set of courses that lead to a direct industry employment for the students, while being in direct communication with the industry all the time - from course and sub-curriculum design to monthly progress of student learning portfolios. For example, UET and Mentor Graphics have successfully done this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice for an accreditor and university head:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the university and department can guarantee that it is fulfilling a certain demand of the industry successfully up to graduate placement, then that is really it, they don&amp;rsquo;t have to worry about catering to generic program requirements. Perhaps your students wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be able to get into a masters program, but that&amp;rsquo;s okay. But this requires guts and clarity of thought in university heads, because a typical accreditor would inquire about one missing course or another, just because in their own undergrad they took that. E.g. it is an outdated concept that all electrical engineers have to know controls theory, communications theory, signal processing, logic design etc.
Thankfully, unlike EE&amp;rsquo;s accreditation bodies and employability issues, computer science is fortunate that it does not have a stringent PEC equivalent and on the other end, the software industry is very vibrant. So especially those universities who have smaller batch sizes, they should be able to align their purpose and objective with their output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice for industry and academic higher-ups:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s technical higher education problem cannot be solved from the supplier side. It is physically impossible to pump more resources and technically competent people inside universities and solve the problem, it will be solved by the demand side. An industry that demands high quality graduates, demands that graduates should know certain things and then rewards them for that, i.e. if there is such a student, a great job is guaranteed, that&amp;rsquo;s how the problem will be solved. Right now, the students don&amp;rsquo;t believe that if they know their stuff, they&amp;rsquo;ll get a good job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advice for a rockstar faculty member:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most competent faculty members who are great in academia as well as industry, should get into industry and help build the demand side more, as there are so many kinds of things possible in the software world right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-word-for-recomputepk&#34;&gt;A word for ReCompute.pk:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bilal is of the opinion that we definitely need discourse generating, focused journalism on science as well as higher education, as it would be a great alternative to typical 7-9pm tv talk shows. Most of the young generation is now streaming different content on social media. The mass media&amp;rsquo;s dominant format is that of highlighting conflict, while in nature not everything is in conflict or needs to be presented as such. ReCompute podcasts is such an effort, creating and curating constructive conversations for the academia.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ReCompute with Aamir Shahzad | Purpose of Education, Pakistani vs Foreign Universities, Root Causes | Podcast # 1</title>
      <link>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/april-03-2021-chat-with-aamir/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://recompute-pk.github.io/post/april-03-2021-chat-with-aamir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Aamir Shahzad has studied at NUST and LUMS in Pakistan. But he&amp;rsquo;s also experienced being a student and researcher in France, Sweden, China, Singapore and Russia. As a teacher, he has experienced working at 5 Pakistani universities, and has been involved in curriculum development at departmental level as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ei2_Y715J8I&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;&#34; allowfullscreen title=&#34;YouTube Video&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-aamir&#34;&gt;Why Aamir?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This profile makes Aamir a great choice for giving us a cross-sectional tour of a computer science teacher who is simultaneously bound by department&amp;rsquo;s curricular choices as well as university&amp;rsquo;s culture and priorities, while cross comparing with &amp;lsquo;baahir ki universities.&amp;rsquo; Secondly, Aamir being an idealist, always is cognizant of the fact that there is a difference between what is happening in our universities and what ought to be. He&amp;rsquo;ll unfold both within this conversation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;purpose-of-education&#34;&gt;Purpose of education:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make ourselves a better human being, and to make the world where we&amp;rsquo;re placed a better place to live in. But more recently, we&amp;rsquo;ve left this purpose behind and are more focused on skills, tied to monetary terms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;purpose-of-cs-education&#34;&gt;Purpose of CS Education:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In CS education, we can easily see the technical side of the things, and how they are related to making the world a technological convenience for a common man, but on the ethical side, or the higher purposes of education, or the humanities side of the curriculum, there is a glaring gap at the moment. Though there are some courses in CS curriculum in that direction, but neither the university nor the students take those courses seriously, as all the focus is placed on technical courses, lopsidedly. His undergrad&amp;rsquo;s Pakistan Studies teacher left an impact on Aamir, so he clearly sees the significance of non-technical courses for shaping students. One way to bridge the gap is to introduce a historical context within the content of technical courses as well, instead of just teaching the finished models. This will help develop process thinking in students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;state-of-pakistani-universities&#34;&gt;State of Pakistani universities:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4 years is a sufficient time for training and producing a graduate in whose personality the objectives of the institution should be visible, just like it is with the army personnel, but unfortunately in Pakistani universities those objectives aren&amp;rsquo;t clear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;difference-between-our-and-international-universities&#34;&gt;Difference between our and international universities:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment the Pakistani universities are neither producing thoughtful citizens nor competent technicians. But what is amiss here? Aamir said that Russian, French, or even Chinese universities have a national vision for education, aligned with their national missions. In schools and then even in universities, the teachers as well as students are very serious about achieving those objectives, resulting in students and teachers engaged in labs day and night. Russia and some other countries are bringing computational thinking down to early schooling levels even. Like gym instructors, senior professors are training students for maths and computing Olympiads, in the process polishing students&#39; problem solving skills. When Russian university in which Aamir was based, prioritized research over other aspects, there were big scientist names all around the students to look up to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;pushing-past-symptoms-and-getting-to-the-root-causes&#34;&gt;Pushing past symptoms and getting to the root causes:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even those countries that are not as planned and controlled a state as the socialist blocks, for instance America, Canada, UK etc, where individual and academic freedom triumphs, even they have done incredibly well in science and technology, what is the case with Pakistan? Aamir cites a dialogue from Lewis Carol&amp;rsquo;s Alice in Wonderland, &amp;lsquo;If you don&amp;rsquo;t know where to go, you can take any path.&amp;rsquo; We have policy makers, curriculum designers, accreditation councils but they don&amp;rsquo;t know where to take our education system, resulting in arbitrariness and loop holes. For example, in one university, in the 8th and last semester it was decided that the students must be taught introduction to data science, but the same students had already studied Big data analytics in the 4th semester. To top it, the teacher is asked only to teach the theory within class, without dedicating any support resources for programming or Anaconda labs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Sweden, when they have decided that faculty workload is to be distributed 80% for research and 20% for teaching and administration, then they provide lots of creative teaching and administrative support for the professor, even for that 20%, and for the 80%, they provide utter solitude spaces where the professors can relax and do their thinking, lost in their own worlds. It&amp;rsquo;s in this environment that university&amp;rsquo;s purpose of creation of knowledge gets realized. Meanwhile in Pakistan, at the hiring stage, a mix of teaching and publication abilities are judged, and then almost without any teaching and administrative support, faculty member is made to teach 3-4 courses every semester, and yet at the end of the year faculty members are appraised based on research output, for which neither space not time was ensured by the university in the first place. This confusion in the administration eventually seeps to the students through teachers. Strangely, in this Pakistani environment, top &amp;ldquo;researchers&amp;rdquo; are also often those who are deeply involved in administrative affairs. Russia has kept this adaptive behaviour at bay by having separate teaching and research tracks and objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;positively-moving-forward-for-improving-cs-education&#34;&gt;Positively moving forward for improving CS education:&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike these great nations, we have to admit that Pakistan has no national level vision 2030 or 2050. This results in every government cooking up arbitrary policies, similarly HEC hands out various policies, while the confusion deepens. But we can&amp;rsquo;t really wait and do nothing till that visionary day finally arrives. Pragmatically speaking, what can good CS faculty members decide to do in their departments or courses for their students, despite the known issues elaborated above? Aamir had great practical tips:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just ensure rigor in two things: programming skills and analytical/problem solving sills. Do this in every course, e.g. even discrete maths course should have lots of programming assignments. Students as well as the industry would welcome the positive effect this consistent effort would create in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another pragmatic solution for at least producing great software engineers for the industry by current universities is to set a much higher passing criteria for the core computing courses, programming fundamentals, algorithms etc. Secondly, if the teacher himself or herself has weak programming skills, the industry will keep getting frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We thank Aamir for such an insightful conversation, and giving simultaneous food for thought for policy makers, curriculum developers, heads of institutions and departments as well as faculty members and students. We hope that these meaningful conversations blossom into fruitful national level discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
